Simon, Carleton; Papers apap073
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Carleton P. Simon Papers
1881-1952, 1956
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap073
2.0 cubic ft.
The collection of papers is about drugs and drug related crimes in the United States. It is written by Carleton P. Simon. Simon is a psychiatrist by profession and is very much interested in crimes. This passion led to his next profession as a criminlogist. His writings focus on crimes and examine the motives behind the crimes. Simons has also written fiction magazines and poems.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript collection were purchased from Charles Apfelbaum, a dealer in rare books and collections, by the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, on November 22, 1988.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Administrative History
Carleton Simon was born on the 28th of February 1871 in New York City and attended college in Vienna and Paris, graduating with an M.D. in 1890. In 1893, he married Monetta Worthington Marler. The couple had two children, Rosa and Carleton, Jr.
A psychiatrist by profession, Simon became interested in the criminal mind, and that interest eventually led to his career as a criminologist. In 1901, Simon conducted a psychiatric study of Leon Czolgosz, the assassin of President McKinley. Also in 1901, he studied the water cure, a torture used by the U.S. Army to interrogate Philippine prisoners, at the request of the New York Herald. His findings led to the abolition of this form of questioning.
Phrenology was an early interest of Simon's. In 1904, George Francis Train, an American eccentric who financed the Union Pacific Railway, built the first tramway in England and ran the first clipper ships to Australia, left his brain to Simon, who dissected it and made a report to the American Institute of Phrenology. Carleton Simon also believed that the face was an indicator of personality and that a criminal's face was therefore a mirror into his actions; Some facial characteristics Simon believed were congenital, but most he thought were caused by the etching of experience on the face.
From 1918 to 1920, Simon examined addicts for the New York State Narcotic Commission. In 1920, he was appointed Special Deputy Police Commissioner in charge of the Narcotics Bureau. Simon was credited with increasing the number of people arrested for drug related crimes, In 1921, Simon was also responsible for the formation of the International Narcotic Criminal Identification Bureau which collected records, including photography and fingerprints, an over 100,000 people convicted of narcotic-connected crimes in 700 cities in the United States and 27 foreign countries. Following his tenure as deputy commissioner, Simon compiled a narcotic survey for the state of Louisiana which estimated the number of addicts and the extent of drug trafficking in the state.
From 1928 to 1938, Simon served as special adviser to the Will Hays Commission, which developed a production code that all the movie studios agreed to follow. Simon's role was to read proposed film scripts and to watch movies to ensure that crime was not being glorified. He also advised about whether certain films were indirect causes to specific crimes.
Simon was an advocate of universal, compulsory fingerprinting and of the use of identification badges as means of establishing positive identity. In 1936 he and Dr. Isadore Goldstein developed a retinal method of identification whereby a photograph was made of the pattern of blood vessels of the retina. This method was supposed to be superior to fingerprinting because the pattern of blood vessels could not be changed whereas fingerprints could at least be disfigured.
Carleton Simon had other interests besides criminology. He was known as "The Father of Casting" and was World Surf Casting Champion from 1914 to 1919. In 1914, he organized the Association of Surf Angling Clubs. He wrote about fish and fishing under the pseudonyms Baron Munchausen, Grape Juice, and John O'Neill. He also wrote poems, a few of which were published in newspaper, under the name "The Ancient Mariner," Carlisle Simon, his own name and anonymously. At least a couple of police stories that fictionalized his experience at the NY Police Department were published under the name Charles Somerville.
Carleton Simon continued to present his ideal as a criminologist to the public in his last years. He gave addresses, often to law enforcement organizations, and continued to write. He was the criminologist for the New York State and the New England associations for Chiefs of Police. He died on the eighteenth of February 1951, just before his eightieth birthday.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection consists of the writings of Carleton Simon, mostly on crime, but also included are a couple of stories published under a pseudonym in a detective fiction magazine and a few poems. The pamphlets and other published writings, together with the unpublished writings, give fairly complete view of Simon's ideas on crime and criminology. Although Simon was particularly interested in crimes related to narcotics, his pamphlets and speeches show an interest in a wide range of crimes and in examining the causes of crime and how those might be eliminated. Some of his pamphlets are missing from this collection, notably one written about his examination of Leon Czolgosz. In addition, there is no documentation in the collection of his research of the water cure at the request of the New York Herald.
Many of his unpublished writings are speeches to law enforcement groups and a few of these pieces are drafts of published essays. Besides these, there are a few books that Simon had worked on. One, "Spotting the Junkies", seems to be nearly finished, but it was never published. The book is a description of the lives of drug addicts, and it includes many illustrations, mostly of drug paraphernalia. There is also a folder titled "Criminal Word Book" which apparently was intended to be a glossary of criminals' slang. This work appears to be an early draft and consists of little more than illustrations many of which seem to have been borrowed from the manuscript for "Spotting the Junkies". A third unpublished work consists of two draft chapters describing the lives of individual addicts.
The correspondence and newspaper clippings contain articles about Simon's work and a few letters, notably his correspondence with Sir Percy Sillitoe, a Scottish law enforcement officer. Also included are subject files on specific projects of Simon's: his psychiatric clinic in the Bowery Mission, his part in proving the sanity of a Swedish immigrant, May Johnson, and his interest in his friend George Francis Train.
The series on the Hay's Code contains reports by Simon on the suitability of certain movies and scripts. It shows the morals of the time and how the movie industry attempted to protect itself from public censure by developing a commission that would devise and regulate a production code A the entire movie industry. Simon appears to have been chosen to report on films that use crime as a central element in the plot because of his renown as a criminologist. Simon's role was to determine if any of the films glorified crime or the actions of criminals.
The biographical files contain distilled information about Simon's accomplishments which are augmented by the published news stories about his work as a criminologist.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged into eight series.
Series 1: Biographical Files. 1894, 1901, 1911, 1915-52, 1956. 4 in.
Series 2: Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings. 1881, 1911, 1920-26, 1931-37, 1940-50. 3 in.
Series 3: Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton Simon. 1901, 1904-05, 1919-52. 6 in.
Series 4: Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon. 1900-25, 1935-38, 1940-48. 7 in.
Series 5: The Hay's Code. 1926-37, 1946, 1940. 2.5 in.
Series 6: Photographs. 1900, 1925, 1936, 1938, 1944, 1950. 1.5 in.
Series 7: Memorabilia. 1982-1889, 1094-96, 1902, 1907, 1911-50. 3 in.
Series 8: Publications About Carleton Simon and His Work. 1900, 1906, 1921, 1923-34, 1935, 1939, 1949. 1 in.
Criminal Justice and Prisons; Criminology--United States; Drugs; Scrapbooks; Newsletters; Administrative records; Programs (documents); Photographs; CARLETON P. SIMON PAPERS,(APAP-073)
- Biographical Files, 1894; 1901; 1911 p915-52; 1956; 1; 4 in.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Scope and Contents
  Vitae and brief biographies of Carleton Simon, along with other biographical items, including his will, obituaries, and professional certificates.
  - Brief Biographies of Carleton Simon, 1924-1925; 1933; 1936 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 1)
  - Funeral and Memorial Documents and the Final Letters of Simon, 1949-1951; 1956 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 2)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1911; 1954 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 4)
  - Professional Certificates., 1894; 1901; 1915-1948; 1951 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 5)
  - Tax Returns, 1917-1945; 1918-1945 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 6)
  - Tax Returns, 1917-1951; 1918-1945 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files.), Folder 7)
- Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings, 1881; 1911; 1920-1926; 1931-1937; 1940-1950; 2; 3 in.
  Separate files for incoming correspondence and newspaper clippings, as well as three subject files which include both correspondence and newspaper clippings on some of Simon's projects.
  - Correspondence, 1881; 1911; 1922-1925; 1931-1937; 1941-1949 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings Concerning Simon's Efforts Against Crime, 1920-1926; 1931-1937; 1945; 1950 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from Sir Percy Sillitoe, 1935; 1943-1950 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings on May Johnson's Alleged Insanity, 1948-1950 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings on Simon's Psychiatric Clinic in the Bowery Mission, 1931-1932 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings and Notes on George Francis Train, 1904; 1931 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings on Carleton Simon and His Cases, 1920-1921; 1931-1932; 1937; 1950 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings.), Folder 14)
- Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton Simon, 1901; 1904-1905; 1919-1952; 3; 6 in.
  Arranged alphabetically by title, except for two partial lists of pamphlets that precede the alphabetical listing.
  Many pamphlets by Simon giving his views an crime, a couple of pseudonymous short stories, and two anonymous poems.
  - Partial Lists of Pamphlets (written by Simon and his family), ca. 1950-1952 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 15)
  - Address at the 1925 Meeting of the International Police Conference (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 16)
  - Address to the American Institute of Phrenology, 1904 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 17)
  - Address to the 44th Annual Public Meeting of the New England Watch and Ward Society, 1922 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 18)
  - Alcoholism... Report of the Social Protection Committee, 1950 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 19)
  - Basic Causes of Crime, 1929 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 20)
  - The Causes of Juvenile Delinquency, 1937 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 21)
  - The Clue of the Tattooed Man(under the pseudonym Charles Somerville), 1923 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 22)
  - Crime and the Motion Picture, 1928 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 23)
  - The Crime of Counterfeiting, 1939 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 24)
  - The Criminal Problems of a Big City, 1920 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 25)
  - Control of Narcotics, 1923 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 26)
  - Divorce and its Relation to Crime, 1947 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 27)
  - Dual Personality and Abnormal Behavior, 1949 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 28)
  - Dual Personality and Crime, ca. 1945 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 29)
  - Dual Personality and the Mental Trends in Criminals, 1930 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 30)
  - Facial Indicators of Personality, 1950 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 31)
  - 47th Annual Conference of New York State Chiefs of Police--Publication with Address by and Biography of Simon, 1947 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 32)
  - The Gangster, 1932 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 33)
  - Homosexualists and Sex Crimes, 1947 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 34)
  - The Influence of Heredity and Environment Upon Crime, 1931 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 35)
  - Medico-Legal Problems of the Drug Evil, 1919 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 36)
  - The Menace of Dope, 1924 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 37)
  - The Musical Temperament, ca. 1905 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 38)
  - My Plea at the Bar of Justice, 1920 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 39)
  - Narcotic Survey of the State of Louisiana, 1926 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 40)
  - Narcotics and Crime, 1923 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 41)
  - The Negro Criminal, 1934 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 42)
  - Observation and Its Importance to the Police, 1931 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 43)
  - Onward March of Law Through Historic Crimes(series of newspaper stories), 1937 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 44)
  - "Over-worked" (Poem), 1901 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 45)
  - A Perverted Personality, ca. 1930 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 46)
  - Plants That Incite to Crime, ca. 1935 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 47)
  - Postwar Criminal Problems, ca. 1944 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 48)
  - The Problem of Suicide, 1948 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 49)
  - Program for Annual Ball of the Honor Legion of the New York City Police Department, 1923 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 50)
  - Pyromania and Kleptomania, 1949 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 51)
  - Scientific Discussions of Causes of Behavior, 1940 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 52)
  - Social Problems, 1950 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 53)
  - Solution by Circles, 1941 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 54)
  - Something You Should Know, ca. 1945 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 55)
  - Statement Before the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives, 1930 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 56)
  - A Study of Inheritance, Mental, Physical and Prenatal, ca. 1905 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 57)
  - Survey of the Narcotic Problem, 1924 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 58)
  - The Tap an the Door(under the pseudonym Charles Somerville), 1923 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 59)
  - Unexplainable Phenomena, 1930 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 60)
  - "A Valentine for My Children" (Poem), 1901 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 61)
  - The War Against Criminal Forces, 1942 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 62)
  - What are the Basic Causes of Present Day Crime?, 1929 (Box 1 (3-Pamphlets and Other Published Material by Carleton), Folder 63)
- Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon., 1900-1925; 1935-1936; 1940-1943; 4; 7 in
  Unpublished speeches by Simon, essays on crime and criminological techniques, poems (some that were published in newspapers), the illustrations from a glossary on the slang of criminals, Criminal World Book, which appears to include some illustrations also intended for his book, "Spotting the Junkies", and opening chapters for a third book on the lives of New York City addicts.
  - Address at the Convention of the New York Stale Association of Chiefs of Police, 1936 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 64)
  - Address on Narcotic Drug Addiction, 1925 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 65)
  - Address on Suicide, 1948 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 66)
  - Address to Secret Service on the Psychological Aspect of the Criminal, 1941 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 67)
  - The Cost of Incendiaries and Practical Solutions, 1933 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 68)
  - The Criminal and his Facial Aspects, 1934 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 69)
  - Criminal Lives, 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 70)
  - Criminal Narcotic Drug Addiction--A World Wide Police Problem, 1922 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 71)
  - Criminal Word Book--Illustrations, ca. 1935 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 72)
  - The Danger of Indiscriminate Use of Red and Green Lights on our Public Highways, 1933 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 73)
  - Drafts of the First Two Chapters of a Nonfiction Book an Individual New York City Addicts, ca. 1940 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 74)
  - Lectures and Notes for Lectures at the School for Detectives, 1923-1924 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 75)
  - Narcotic Control, 1923 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 76)
  - The Negro Criminal, 1933 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 77)
  - New Aspects of Criminal Science, 1948 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 78)
  - New Methods for Protecting Public Welfare, 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 79)
  - A New Scientific Method of Identification, 1935 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 80)
  - The Phenomena of Life and Death, ca. 1935 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 81)
  - Plan for New England Association of Chiefs of Police Crime Detection Laboratory, 1933 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 82)
  - Plan for the New York State Association of Chiefs of Police School and Crime Detection Laboratory, 1934 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 83)
  - Poems, 1900-1920 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 84)
  - Post-War Crime Problems and Their Control, 1944 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 85)
  - Remarks an Social Protection Measures, 1946 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 86)
  - Report of the Committee of Criminal Science of the New England Association of Chiefs of Police, 1933 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 87)
  - Resolutions of the New England Association of Chiefs of Police on Fingerprinting and Parole, 1942 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 88)
  - The Retinal Method of Identification, 1936 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 89)
  - Simon-Goldstein Scientific Method of Identification, ca. 1936 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 90)
  - Simon-Goldstein Scientific Method of Identification, ca. 1936 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 91)
  - Spotting the "Junkies,", ca. 1935 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 92)
  - Spotting the Junkies "Contents", 1935 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 1)
  - Spotting the "Junkies" Pages 301 – 342, 1935 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 2)
  - Talk Given by Dr. Carleton Simon on "We, the PeopIe" Subject Marijuana, 1938 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 3)
  - Untitled Essay on Color, ca. 1940 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 4)
  - Statement Before the U.S. Senate Sub-Committee on Racketeering, 1933 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Carleton Simon, 1900; 1925; 1944; 1950 (Box 2 (4-Unpublished Writings by Carleton Simon.), Folder 6)
- The Hay's Code, 1926-1937; 1946; 1948.; 5; 2.5 in.
  Correspondence to and from the Hay's Commission about the suitability of proposed movie scripts and finished movies, and correspondence about the connection between specific crimes and films. Also contains formal reports on specific movies and scripts.
  - Copies of the Code, 1930 (Box 2 (5-The Hay's Code), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Folder 1, 1926-1931 (Box 2 (5-The Hay's Code), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Folder 2, 1928-1937; 1946; 1948 (Box 2 (5-The Hay's Code), Folder 9)
  - Simon's Reports on Motion Pictures, 1926-1934; 1937 (Box 2 (5-The Hay's Code), Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1900; 1925; 1930-1936; 1944; 1950; 6; 1.5 in.
  Arranged by subject.
  Two folders of photographs, one of photographs of Carleton Simon and one of photographs of other people, mostly law enforcement officials.
  - Photographs of Carleton Simon, 1900; 1925; 1944; 1950 (Box 3 (6-Photographs), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Others, 1936; 1938 (Box 3 (6-Photographs), Folder 2)
- Memorabilia, 1882-1889; 1884-1896; 1902; 1907; 1917-1950; 7; 3 in.
  Includes a scrapbook, a report card book, a wallet, an address book, blank letterhead, awards, and citations.
  - Address Book and Notebook, ca. 1930-1950 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 15)
  - Awards and Citations, 1946; 1951 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 16)
  - Blank Letterhead, ca. 1930-1950 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 17)
  - Honorary Membership Certificates, 1902; 1907; 1920-1924; 1930-1931; 1943-1949 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 18)
  - Mementos, 1894-1896; 1944 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 19)
  - Phonodisk of a Radio Broadcast from the Series, "Crime is a Losing Game,", 1949 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 20)
  - Plaque from the New York City Police Department, ca. 1940 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 21)
  - Plaque from the New York City Police Department, 1882-1983 (Box 3 (7-Memorabilia), Folder 22)